Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-22; Obverse Column 1 1. … 2. … 3. … 4. … 5. The white mes tree 6. The black mes tree 7. The mes wood from Magan 8. The mes wood from the sea of Meluhha 9. A type of mes wood 10. A type of tree 11. A type of willow 12. A type of tree 13. … 14. A type of tree 15. An olive tree 16. An almond tree 17. A type of plant 18. A type of tree 19. A type of cedar 20. A sycamore 21. A type of sycamore 22. A type of tree 23. A Prunus Mahaleb tree 24. A reed object 25. … 26. A camel thorn plant 27. … 28. … 29. … 30. … Column 2 (Approximately 6 lines missing) 7'. … 8'. … 9'. … 10'. … 11'. … 12'. … 13'. … 14'. … 15'. A type of wood or plant 16'. An offshoot 17'. … 18'. A forest 19'. A forest consumed by fire 20'. A forest eaten by insects 21'. A chaste tree 22'. A type of tree 23'. A type of tree 24'. A conifer tree 25'. A terebinth 26'. An almond tree 27'. … 28'. A plum tree 29'. A grapevine 30'. A mountain grapevine 31'. A fox grape 32'. A type of tree 33'. A mountain ildag tree Column 3 1. An ildag sapling 2. An ildag tree of the water channel 3. A cedar tree 4. A type of cedar tree 5. A thorny tree 6. A thorny tree from Meluhha 7. A terebinth tree 8. A small terebinth tree 9. An oak tree 10. … 11. … 12. … 13. A type of plant 14. … 15. A goadstick 16. A goadstick 17. … 18. … 19. A type of tree 20. A pine tree 21. A pine cone 22. A pine tree seed 23. A crown of pine tree 24. A cut pine bough 25. An apple tree 26. A quince tree 27. An apricot tree 28. A pomegranate tree 29. A type of juniper 30. A juniper tree 31. … 32. A type of fruit tree Column 4 1. A poplar tree 2. A mountain poplar tree 3. A poplar seed 4. … 5. A board 6. … 7. Upper foliage 8. A type of foliage 9. A date palm 10. A mountain date palm 11. A date palm offshoot 12. A split date palm 13. A pruned date palm 14. A date palm fiber 15. A harness for climbing date palms 16. The midrib of a date palm frond 17. A date palm offshoot 18. … 19. A young date palm frond 20. A cut date palm frond midrib with leaflets 21. A heart of palm 22. Hearts of palm 23. … 24. The broom of a date palm frond 25. The stump of a date palm frond 26. … 27. A date palm crossbar 28. A type of date palm stump 29. A date palm fiber 30. … 31. … 32. A date palm frond 33. A date palm frond 34. Date palm fronds 35. … 36. A date palm crown 37. … Reverse 1. A cut off tree branch 2. A sign 3. A plow 4. A manual plow 5. A fully-equipped plow 6. A plow not fully-equipped 7. A breaking plow 8. A part of the plow attached to the side of the ox 9. The front of the plow 10. … 11. … 12. … 13. … 14. … 15. A plow's share 16. A part of the plow connecting the team to the yoke 17. The plow's arm 18. The sideboard of the plow 19. The board of the plow 20. The vessel of the plow 21. The earring of the plow 22. The yoke of the plow 23. The pole of the plow 24. … 25. The hoe of the plow 26. A hoe 27. A toothed hoe 28. A two-toothed hoe 29. A three-toothed hoe 30. A four-toothed hoe 31. A wooden vessel 32. Rotten wood 33. Rotten wood 34. Rotten wood 35. Ebony wood 36. A type of stick 37. A type of stick 38. A ball 39. A stick 40. A ball 41. A log 42. A type of mountain tree 43. Kindling wood 44. … 45. … 46. … 47. … 48. A … peg 49. A wagon 50. The pivot of a wagon 51. … 52. … 53. A handle 54. … 55. A towed boat 56. … 57. … Column 2 1. The wheel of a wagon 2. The peg of the wheel of a wagon 3. … 4. A wagon hitch 5. A part of a wagon 6. The chair of a wagon 7. The sleeping place of a wagon 8. … 9. The handle of a wagon 10. A … vehicle 11. A … vehicle 12. A vehicle for the field 13. A harrow 14. A pivot of the harrow 15. A peg in the pivot of a harrow 16. … 17. A large-toothed harrow 18. A shovel 19. A winnowing shovel 20. A bread trowel 21. … 22. A kiln trowel 23. … 24. … 25. The wooden handle of a shovel 26. A measuring container of 60 liters 27. A measuring container 28. A measuring container of two liters 29. A measuring container of 10 liters 30. A measuring container of five liters 31. A measuring container of one liter 32. A measuring container of a half liter 33. A measuring container of one-third liter 34. A measuring container of ten shekels 35. A measuring container of five shekels 36. A measuring container of one shekel 37. A measuring container of one-half shekel 38. A measuring container of one-third shekel 39. … 40. … 41. An axe 42. A footstool 43. A copper footstool 44. A footstool decorated with ivory 45. A chair 46. … 47. … 48. A tall chair 49. A chair for travelling 50. … 51. … 52. … 53. … 54. A root 55. A root Column 3 1. … 2. … 3. A sailor's chair 4. A copper chair 5. A woman's chair 6. A man's chair 7. A chair for the assembly 8. A chair built from palm fibers 9. A chair built from … 10. A chair with knobs inlaid with bronze 11. A chair with knobs inlaid with silver 12. A chair with knobs inlaid with gold 13. A chair of a king 14. The board of a chair 15. The front of a chair 16. The rung of a chair 17. A bed 18. A couch 21. A bed built from … 22. A bed with a carded wool mattress 23. A bed with a mattress of nanny hair 24. A bed with legs shaped like an ox's hoof 25. A bed with thin wheels 26. … 27. A bed board 28. The front of a bed 29. A bed rung 30. A type of loom (Approximately 10 lines missing); 7 1/4"height x 6 1/2" width x 1 1/8" depth, large rectangular multi-column tablet joined from fragments; A large but broken tablet that has been reassembled from six fragments. The two larger broken and reattached corners have been adhered with multiple, unknown, adhesives, one of which has a greenish-gray hue. Another corner has been broken into multiple fragments, two of which have been readhered, along with an edge fragment. These three repairs were made with the greenish-gray adhesive and are poorly fit; there also appears to be some straw-like material set in the adhesive. There are vertical but incomplete cracks on one face. There is a surface loss to one of the larger, readhered corners. (Drawer S2)
- School text, lexical exercise from Proto-Lu., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-14; 5 9/16" height x 3 15/16" width x 1 3/8" depth, large rectangular multi-column tablet; Rectangular tablet with one inscribed face mostly intact and the opposite face with about half of the inscribed surface lost to spalling. About half of one short side of the intact face is broken off and is lost. Almost all of the opposite short side is broken and lost, except one corner that is damaged by a gouge. One long side of this face is broken and spalled, creating a diagonal edge. There are some shiny white deposits on this face- mostly on one end- that may be salt. The opposite face has lost about 2/3 of the inscribed surface to spalling. Only one corner is intact; a second corner is broken and lost; and one whole short side is broken and badly spalled. A deep crack within the tablet is visible at the broken short side. A hairline crack runs from the broken/spalled short side toward the center of this face. (Drawer S3)
  This is a basic vocabulary exercise in writing various types of professions.
- School text, lexical exercise of types of pots., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.8; 1. A pot with a perforated bottom 2. A brewing vat; 2 15/16" diameter x 13/16" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet has several incomplete cracks overall on the uninscribed face. There cracks may possibly lead to spalling (?) There are some minor surface losses overall. There are some white concrections visible overall. There is a small, cream-colored label adhered to the uninscribed face near the edge that has a typed number "8". (Drawer 1)
  This short exercise lists a student's practice vocabulary for types of pots.
- School text, mathematical exercise of surveying., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-25; 3" height x 3 7/16" width x 1 1/8" depth, rectangular tablet; Rectangular tablet with several complete and incomplete cracks throughout. There are losses at one corner and minor losses in another corner. There are also minor losses to the surface of the tablet overall. There are white and tan concretions visible on the surface overall. There is one noticeable deposit near one corner -- this could possibly be dirt. (Drawer 2)
  This student exercise is practice in drawing the layout of a large estate complete with irrigation and field boundaries. The reverse has been erased.
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-1A; (Too broken to reconstruct); 2 3/8" height x 1 7/8" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet that is slightly misshapen. One half end of the tablet is slightly wider than the other half. Two corners on the thinner half are bent upward slightly on the uninscribed face. Additionally, one half of the uninscribed face is thicker than the other half by about 1/8" - 1/4". There is a loss in one corner on this face that has left the surface uneven and jagged. There is also a groove mark across this face that looks to have been made with a modern tool. There is another gouge on one of the edges although it is difficult to tell when this was made because the patina is similar to that of the non-damaged portions of the tablet. There is a groove on an edge was still wet. The inscribed face looks worn. There is a loss at one corner and the surface at another corner may possibly have been scraped when the clay was still wet. There are white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 3)
  This student vocabular exercise is taken from the Old Babylonian Ura 1 list of wooden objects.
- School text, envelope fragment with sealing., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); SC-IV-8; Reverse 1. Month: 'Seed' 2. Year: 'Simurrum and Lullubum were damaged for the 9th time.' Seal 1. 'His father', 2. A scribe 3. Son of …; 1 15/16" height x 1 11/16" width x 15/16" depth, baked square envelope; Rectangular cuneiform tablet envelope fragment. A large portion of the envelope is lost. Additionally, there are some surface losses. The edges and surface are jagged where there are losses. There are some incomplete cracks and folds in the clay visible on the interior of the envelope. There are incomplete cracks visible at a corner edge. There are some gouge marks on two of the edges that were most likely made with a modern tool. (Drawer 4)
  This administrative document was written by Abu-shuni in the ancient city of Umma and dates to Shulgi 44 (c. 2099 BCE), month
  6. There is no writing preserved inside envelope.
- School text, sign exercise from TU-TA-TI and letter exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 135; 3 5/8" height x 2 1/4" width x 1 1/4" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet with transposed writing on the reverse; The tablet is misshapen; slightly rounded (concave on one face, convex on the other). One corner is pushed up into the body. Deformation clearly took place when the clay was still wet. There are deep "cuts" in two places on one face. There is no adhesive or surface coating. The tablet appears very stable. (Drawer 5)
  This student exercise has the introduction to a letter on the obverse, which has been drawn over in antiquity. The reverse has both part of a letter and a section of TU-TA-TI transposed.
- School text, lexical exercise from Proto-Ea with pronunciation glosses., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 89; Obverse Column 1 3'. … 4'. … 5'. … 6'. City 7'. … 8'. … 9'. Dagger 10'. … 11'. A bush 12'. Burn 13'. Wool 14'. Stone cutter 15'. A fly 16'. … 17'. … 18'. To place Column 2 1. … 2. … 3. To break 4. A ration 5. A ration 6. To press 7. To spread 8. … 9. Youth 10. To dig 11. … 12. Pig 13. To winnow 14. … 15. Place 16. … 17. To speak 18. Equal 19. Healthy Reverse Column 1 1. Stomach 2. Hand 3. Large 4. … 5. Non-precious stone 6. Hill 7. Month 8. Priest 9. Head 10. … 11. … 12. … 13. … 14. Angry 15. … 16. Mouth 17. Word 18. … 19. Tooth Column 2 1. To speak 2. Voice 3. To speak 4. … 5. Skull 6. To go 7. To bring 8. To bring 9. To establish 10. To stand 11. To go 12. … 13. … 14. To bring 15. …; 4 1/4" height x 2 1/8" width x 7/8" depth, red rectangular double column tablet; There is a large loss to one corner and a smaller loss of an adjacent corner. No adhesive is present. Tablet appears well fired; the surface does not appear to be coated. (Drawer 6)
- School text, mathematical exercise of a multiplication table., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 4; 6 3/4" height x 5 5/16" width x 1 1/4" depth, large rectangular multi-column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into four pieces. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. This clear adhesive is visible along the breaks. One of the pieces was not properly aligned when reattached and/or there are several losses along this break, because there is a gap between this piece and the other two pieces. There is a sizeable, deep loss at the center of the tablet where the breaks converge. There is another loss to the surface of the flat face at a center edge. There are losses to two of the corners. There are other losses to the surface overall, as well as losses along the breaks. There are several incomplete cracks visible overall. There are some patches of a a transluscent white substance overall. There are some small white concretions visible in the crevices of one of the corner losses and in some of the cuneiform impressions as well. (Drawer S2)
  This text is a student practice problem based on a multiplication table for 50. The reverse contains area measurements.
- School text., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.14; 1. The sun god brings the bread, 2. He knows its words. 3. The lady brings the bread, 4. She knows its life.; 3 1/8" diameter x 5/8" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet has a lot of damage to its surface on the inscribed face. There are several shallow losses, many of which are circular. Possibly these were made with a tool (?). On the uninscribed face, there are several incomplete cracks and a lot of spalling. There is a gouge near one edge and scratch marks overall although it is unclear if these were made while the clay was still wet, or after the tablet dried. There are some other minor chips to the surface on this face and on the edges. The surface of the tablet, particularly on the inscribed face is a mottled black and brown color. There are white concretions visible overall. There is a small, cream-colored label typed with the number "14", adhered to the uninscribed face near the edge. (Drawer 1)
  The contents of this student exercise are unclear.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-17; 1. 'My god is …' 2. 'He is the true heir' 3. … 4. 'Suen defeats' 5. … 6. 'His root is sweet'; 3 5/16" height x 2 5/8" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse effaced; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. The flat face has an incomplete crack running down the center. There is also a groove mark on one side of the tablet that looks like it was made with an implement while the clay was still wet. There is a small loss near one corner on this same face. There are some shallow marks on the convex face that seems to be remains of cuneiform impressions (in addition to the clearly impressed cuneiform script at one side). Possibly some of the inscriptions have worn away as there are no groove lines indicating scraping. There is also some minor spalling on this face. There are white concretions overall as well as some salt crystals. There are two irregularities on the edges where it looks like the clay was not completely smoothed or pressed down, or something hit the clay while it was still wet. (Drawer 2)
  This beginner exercise is a student's practice writing personal names.
- School text, mathematical exercise of a multiplication table., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-30; 3 1/4" height x 2" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with a large loss in one corner and a smaller loss in another corner. There is some spalling in the corners with those losses. There are some incomplete cracks in the corner with the smaller loss. There are some white concretions visible mostly around the corner with the smaller loss. (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise is a multiplication table for 1/500.
- School text, lexical exercise fom Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-14; Obverse 1. An apple tree; 2. A quince tree; 3. An arwanum apple tree; 4. A spring(?) apple tree; 5. An … apple tree; 6. An … apple tree; 7. A damshilum apple tree; Reverse 1. A biza apple tree; 2. An …; 3. A fig tree; 1 1/2" height x 2" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; The tablet is mostly intact except for one corner that is broken off and lost. Once face has several deposits of a pale white substance- these deposits may be salt crystals. The deposits vary in size from small to about 1/4-inch across. The opposite face was wiped down on one half; that wiped half has a large deposit at one edge. Both short sides of the tablet also have deposits. (Drawer 4)
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 4., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-15; 3 5/8" height x 2 1/4" width x 13/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that broke into three pieces that where reattached with clear adhesive. One broken piece is a corner; the tablet also broke approximately across the middle. Both faces and three of the sides have adhesive visible on the surface at the breaks, and the adhesive has bled welll beyond the boundaries of the breaks. One face has a small, thin loss along the repaired corner break. The repaired center break has areas of spalling along the repair, particularly at one edge. The long sides of the tablet along this break do not fit together cleanly; there is a small gap where the two broken pieces come together. The opposite face has a deep area of spalling along the corner break and along the second break; both of these areas are heavily covered with adhesive. There is a smalll hole at the approximate center of this face that runs into the interior of the tablet. There are scattered white deposits on this face (one deposit below the corner break is shiny and possibly crystalline). One corner is spalled. (Drawer 5)
  This student vocabular exercise is taken from the Old Babylonian Ura 4 list of stone objects.
- School text, lexical exercise of plant names., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 127; 1. … 2. A type of weed 3. A type of grass 4. A type of grass 5. … 6. A type of cut grass 7. … 8. A type of plant 9. A cobweb 10. … 11. A thorny weed 12. His mother plant 13. His child plant 14. A type of plant 15. Property plant 16. Licorice 17. A type of grass 18. A type of grass 19. Camel plant; 3 5/8" height x 2 1/16" width x 3/4" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet that has broken into three pieces. The three pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There is a deep surface loss on the uninscribed face where the breaks converge. There are other small losses along the breaks at three of the corners as well as on the surface overall. There are incomplete cracks overall. There are patches of a yellow-brown substance on the surface visible throughout -- this is possibly dirt. A coating has been applied to the surface of the tablet. (Drawer 6)
  This elementary student exercise is practice writing basic vocabulary for plants. This text is not part of a known vocabulary list.
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-12; 8 3/8" height x 4 3/16" width x 2 1/8" depth, square prism joined from fragments; A large rectangular tablet with inscriptions retained on only one face. The tablet has been broken into at least two pieces and repaired. The repairs appear to have been made with a white glue/adhesive that was coated with dirt or clay to disguise the repair. One face of the tablet is lost and the remaining piece appears to be approximately 1/2 of a large, perforated tablet. The central channel of the perforation is still visable on the damaged "face". There is a hole on one edge that resembles those made by boring insects. (Drawer S2)
  This student vocabular exercise is taken from the Old Babylonian Ura 1 list of wooden objects. The complete face of the prism is the end of the list, complete with a colophon.
- School text, literary exercise from Iddin-Dagan B., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 38770; 1. He has raised you, 2. he has placed the foreign lands at your feet. 3. Enlil.; 2 7/8" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular cuneiform tablet made of chocolate brown clay. There is a loss at one edge that reveals a lighter brown substance- this substance may be the interior clay of the tablet, or it may be brown fill that is partially filling the break. A small light brown deposit on the surface of the tablet in this same area may be dried fill. About an inch away from the break there are two round gouges on the face. Diagonally across the face from the break, the edge of the tablet is flat rather than curved. This area has the same patina as the rest of the face, so if it is the result of damage, it is old damage. The opposite face also shows the break and loss already described, but it is less prominent on this face. There is a shallow gouge or chip near the loss, toward the center of the face. Near the flattened edge of the tablet, there is a small, oblong hole that reveals part of the interior of the tablet. (Drawer 1)
  This advanced student exercise is from a praise poem of Iddin-Dagan (version B), who was king under the First Dynasty of Isin, from 1974-1954 BCE. This excerpt includes lines 3- 5.
- Letter with envelope and sealing from king Rim-Suen of Larsa., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-20; 5 3/16" height x 2 3/8" width x 1 3/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet with a partial envelope on the obverse face; Long, rectangular tablet with a partial "envelop" still intact on one face. The face with the envelop layer intact has considerable losses and it appears as if the envelop has been chipped away. One corner of the tablet has been broken and lost. An unknown adhesive has been applied in this corner. The clay appears relatively well fired. (Drawer 2)
  This royal letter is from king Rim-Suen to Suen-Imguranni. The Old Babylonian sealing is partially preserved on envelope. Rim-Suen ruled from 1822-1763 BCE.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-34; 1 5/8" height x 1 1/16" width x 5/8" depth, small rectangular tablet; Small rectangular tablet of grey-tan clay. There is a small loss on the surface of one face near a corner edge. On this same face, there are several cracks and wrinkles in the clay. There are some white concretions visible on the surface overall. There is a sheen to the raised portions of the surface, perhaps indicating that the tablet was coated (?) (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise is practice writing large numbers.